Finding Aid for Charles Adam Weissert papers, 1893-1947
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Adam Weissert papers 1893-1947
Weissert, Charles Adam, 1878-1947.
86530 Aa 2; Ac
Journalist, historical researcher from Kalamazoo, Michigan; Correspondence, research articles and notes, and photographs.
3.3 linear feet in 4 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Charles A. Weissert (donor no. 2429 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles A. Weissert was born Aug. 22, 1878 in Hastings, Michigan. He had a varied career as a scholar, author, journalist, and lawmaker. He was a veteran newspaperman working for newspapers in New York, Grand Rapids, Hastings, and Kalamazoo. Weissert traveled widely in his lifetime and became an authority on Michigan history, writings numerous articles and serving as an active member of the Michigan State Historical Society.
Weissert also served in the state legislature, first elected in 1914 and re-elected in 1916 and 1918. While there, he authored the bill requiring all county supervisors to use public funds for marking historical sites and preserving historical material and, as chairman of the House Committee on Military Affairs, Weissert introduced the bill establishing the Michigan State Police in 1919.
He died April 12, 1947.
The Weissert collection includes correspondence, 1893-1947, including letters from Joseph Bailly, Clarence M. Burton, Gurdon S. Hubbard, Chase S. Osborn, Albert E. Sleeper, and George Van Pelt. There are also speeches, and writings mostly on Michigan history topics, including Indian history and the history of Kalamazoo and Barry County. The series of research notes illustrates the variety of Weissert's interests: historical personalities, forts, Michigan cities, and early state history. The photographs and snapshots pertain to Weissert's interest in Michigan history, especially homes, churches, mills, hotels, businesses, and other sites primarily in western Michigan, but also including Sault Ste. Marie and Mackinac Island. There are also photographs of Michigan pioneers, particularly from the Hastings, Michigan area.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Allegan (Mich.); Allouez, Claude, 1622-1689.; Augusta (Mich.); Bailly family.; Baldwin, Charles.; Bandholtz, Harry Hill, 1864-1925.; Bangor (Mich.); Barry, John Stewart, 1802-1870.; Barry County (Mich.); Baseball.; Bloomingdale (Mich.); Brentano, Theodore.; Bronson, Titus, 1788-1853.; Bronson (Mich.); Brown, Reese P.; Buchanan (Mich.); Burnips (Mich.); Campau, Louis, 1791-1871.; Campau family.; Ontario--Boundaries--Michigan.; Cassopolis (Mich.); Centreville (Mich.); Charlotte (Mich.); Climax (Mich.); Clisbee, Charles West, 1833-1889.; Coldwater (Mich.); Coloma (Mich.); Constantine (Mich.); Covert (Mich.); Dutch Americans--Michigan.; Eveleth, William S., d. 1818.; Fort Custer (Mich.); Fort Mackinac (Mackinac Island, Mich.); Fort Saint Joseph (Mich.); Fort Wilkins (Mich.); Freedom (Mich.); Freeport (Mich.); French Americans--Michigan.; Galesburg (Mich.); Ganges (Mich.); Grand Junction (Mich.); Grand Ledge (Mich.); Grand River (Mich.); Mottville (Mich.); Griffon (Ship); Hartford (Mich.); Hastings (Mich.); Hunting--Michigan.; Indiana--Boundaries--Michigan.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Journalists--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Justices of the peace--Michigan.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Kalamazoo College.; Kalamazoo County (Mich.); LaFramboise, Joseph, d. 1809.; Leonidas (Mich.); McCoy, Isaac, 1784-1846.; Marcellus (Mich.); Medicine--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Mendon (Mich.); Michigan--Boundaries--Ontario.; Michigan--Boundaries--Indiana.; Michigan Historical Commission.; Michigan. Legislature (48th: 1915); Monroe (Mich.); Nashville (Mich.); American newspapers--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Orangeville (Mich.); Paw Paw (Mich.); Podunk (Mich.); Potier, Pierre-Philippe, 1708-1781.; Reserve Officers Association of the United States. Dept. of Michigan.; Plank roads--Michigan.; Rochester (Mich.); Saint Joseph County (Mich.); Saint Joseph River (Mich. and Ind.); Saline (Mich.); Saugatuck (Mich.); Savery, Asahel.; Schoolcraft (Mich.); Selkirk, James, 1790-1877.; Shafter, William Rufus, 1835-1906.; Sherwood (Mich.); Singapore (Mich.); Antislavery movements--United States.; South Haven (Mich.); Stearns, Justus S. (Justus Smith), b. 1845.; Striker, Daniel E., 1835-1898.; Sunfield (Mich.); Thessalon (Mich.); Thornapple River (Mich.); Three Oaks (Mich.); Toll, Isaac D., 1818-1908.; Transportation--Michigan.; Underground Railroad--Michigan.; Union City (Mich.); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--War of 1812.; Van Urk, Thomas.; W. K. Kellogg Foundation.; Weissert, Charles Adam, 1878-1947.; White Pigeon (Mich.); World War, 1914-1918.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; Mexican War, 1846-1848.; Ontario--Boundaries--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Aged persons.; Barry County (Mich.); Belle Isle (Detroit, Mich.); Black River (Mich.); Bradley (Mich.)--Missions.; Buildings--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Buildings--Michigan--Saugatuck.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Climax.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Hastings.; Cass County (Mich.); Cassopolis (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Centreville (Mich.)--Courthouses.; Churches.; Climax (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Coldwater (Mich.); Constantine (Mich.); Courthouses--Michigan--Centreville.; Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Cassopolis.; Dwellings--Michigan--Galesburg.; Ferries.; Fort Custer (Mich.); Galesburg (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Hastings (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Harbor Point (Mich.)--Lighthouses.; Hotels and taverns.; Indians of North America.; Interiors.; Hartford (Mich.)--Missions.; Kalamazoo County (Mich.); Kalamazoo (Mich.)--Buildings.; Lighthouses--Michigan--Harbor Point.; Log cabins.; Lumber industry.; Mackinac Island (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Middle Village (Mich.); Military camps.; Military inspections.; Military parades and ceremonies.; Mills.; Missions--Michigan--Bradley.; Missions--Michigan--Hartford.; Monuments and memorials.; Prisoners of war--Germany.; Prisoners of war--United States.; Railroad accidents.; Saint Mary's River (Mich. and Ont.); Saugatuck (Mich.)--Buildings.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Shipping--Great Lakes.; Thornapple River (Mich.); Underground railroad system.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); White Pigeon (Mich.); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 33rd (1898-1899). Company B.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; Spanish-American War, 1898.
Contributors:
Bailly de Messein, Joseph, 1774-1835.; Burton, Clarence Monroe, 1853-1932.; Hubbard, Gurdon Saltonstall, 1802-1886.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Sleeper, Albert E., 1862-1934.; Van Pelt, George W.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal
  - Correspondence 1893-1947, undated, 20 folders (Box 1)
  - Birth certificate, deeds, commissions, etc. (Box 1)
    (see also oversize folder Ac)
- Writings
  - Poems and stories (Box 1)
  - Non-Michigan histories (Box 1)
  - Proposed legislative bills (Box 1)
  - Proposed books on Michigan history and the St. Joseph River (Box 1)
- Speeches
  - "The Michigan Road in Territorial Days" (Box 1)
  - "Early Settlement of Barry County" (Box 1)
  - "Early Settlement of Kalamazoo and its founder, Titus Bronson" (Box 1)
    (see also Bronson photograph file)
  - Speech by Thomas Van Urk reminiscing on his family's arrival from the Netherlands in 1892 (Box 1)
  - Speech by Thomas Van Urk on occasion of his 50th anniversary of his medical practice (Box 1)
  - 1928 speech about Isaac McCoy (Box 1)
  - 1933 speech entitled "Kalamazoo College" (Box 1)
  - 1939 speech about foreign affairs (Box 1)
  - 1939-1941 speeches about national defense (Box 1)
  - Speeches on journalism and news writing (Box 1)
  - Speeches on the Constitution, presidential power, and citizenship (Box 1)
  - Dated speeches 1928-1939 (Box 1)
- Research and collected materials
  - Biographical sketches
    - Charles W. Clisbee (Box 1)
    - Justus S. Stearns (Box 1)
    - Interview with Andrew Campau (Box 1)
  - State Historical Society materials (Box 1)
    (includes minutes, record of books purchased, and an account of a meeting of the Anthony Wayne Memorial Committee)
  - Account book recording business transacted by George Washington for the United States 1775-1783 (Box 1)
  - Typescript of Darius B. Cook's Six Months Among the Indians, typescript copy (Box 1)
  - Materials relating to the French and Indian War and the War of 1812, typescript copy taken from originals in the Public Archives of Canada (Box 1)
  - Paper on James Fennimore Cooper, Lucius Lyon and the W.K. Kellogg Foundation (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of Lizzie Barton of Kalamazoo, Michigan, circa 1878 (Box 1)
    (containing clippings of poems and articles, including some sketches in pencil, pen, and color)
  - Scrapbooks containing historical information on Barry and Kalamazoo counties (Box 3)
    (many of the clippings in these volumes are articles written by CAW)
  - Obituary notices of Barry County residences (Box 3)
  - Records of a Barry County justice of the peace 1857-1858 (Box 3)
- Research notes
  - Notes on the Community Health Project and the W.K. Kellogg Foundation (Box 2)
  - Notes on transportation (Box 2)
  - Notes on "Decouvertes et Etablissements des Francais dans L'Amerique, 1683-1724" by Pierre Margry (Box 2)
  - Notes on "Journal of a Voyage to North America" by Duke de Lesdiquires (1761) (Box 2)
  - Notes on issues reported in the Detroit Journal 1830 (Box 2)
  - Notes on Michigan men in the Mexican War (Box 2)
  - Notes on Michigan in the War of 1812 (Box 2)
  - Notes on Michigan regiments in the Civil War (Box 2)
  - Notes on Michigan Indians who served in the Civil War (Box 2)
  - Notes on the underground railroad in Michigan (Box 2)
  - Notes on Michigan men in the Spanish-American War (Box 2)
  - Notes on Barry County men in World War I (Box 2)
  - Notes on Indians in Michigan, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Notes on LaSalle's ship, the Griffin (Box 2)
  - Notes on turkey shoots in Michigan (Box 2)
  - Notes on wild pigeons in Michigan (Box 2)
  - Notes on the Middle Village (Box 2)
  - Notes on historical personalities
    - Father Allouez (Box 2)
    - Joseph Bailly (Box 2)
    - Charles B. (Lady) Baldwin (Box 2)
      Detroit baseball pitcher in the 1880s
    - General Henry Hill Bandholtz (Box 2)
    - Governor John Steward Barry (Box 2)
    - Judge Theodore Brentana (Box 2)
    - Reese P. Brown (Box 2)
      Cass County abolitionist
    - Christina Hand (Box 2)
    - Thomas C. Hart (Box 2)
    - J. Stanley B. Harvey (Box 2)
    - Sam Houston (Box 2)
    - Frank Lanning (Box 2)
    - Lewis and Clark expedition (Box 2)
    - General Frank Parker (Box 2)
      (see also photograph series)
    - Zebulon Montgomery Pike (Box 2)
    - Asahel Savery (Box 2)
    - Selkirk family (Box 2)
    - General William Shafter (Box 2)
    - Sherman and Comings families (Box 2)
    - S.E. Striker (Box 2)
    - Moses Wisner (Box 2)
  - Notes on forts
    - Fort Custer (Box 2)
    - Fort Mackinac (Box 2)
    - Fort St. Joseph (Box 2)
    - Fort Wilkins (Box 2)
  - Notes on Michigan cities
    - Allegan (Box 2)
    - Augusta (Box 2)
    - Bangor (Box 2)
    - Bloomingdale (Box 2)
    - Bronson (Box 2)
    - Buchanan (Box 2)
    - Burnips (Box 2)
    - Carlton (Box 2)
    - Cassopolis (Box 2)
    - Centreville (Box 2)
    - Charlotte (Box 2)
    - Climax (Box 2)
    - Coldwater (Box 2)
    - Coloma (Box 2)
    - Constantine (Box 2)
    - Covert (Box 2)
    - Freedom (Box 2)
    - Freeport (Box 2)
    - Ganges (Box 2)
    - Grand Junction (Box 2)
    - Grand Ledge (Box 2)
    - Grand Traverse (i.e. Mottville) (Box 2)
    - Hartford (Box 2)
    - Hastings (Box 2)
    - Leonidas (Box 2)
    - Marcellus (Box 2)
    - Mendon (Box 2)
    - Monroe (Box 2)
    - Nashville (Box 2)
    - Orangeville (Box 2)
    - Paw Paw (Box 2)
    - Podunk (Box 2)
    - Rochester (Box 2)
    - Saline (Box 2)
    - Saugatuck (Box 2)
    - Schoolcraft (Box 2)
    - Sherwood (Box 2)
    - Singapore (Box 2)
    - South Haven (Box 2)
    - Sunfield (Box 2)
    - Thornapple (Box 2)
    - Three Oaks (Box 2)
    - White Pigeon (Box 2)
    - Union City (Box 2)
    - Yankee Springs (Box 2)
  - 50 questions on local history (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Group photos (Box 2)
    include groups with CAW; also photo of the men of the 32nd Michigan Infantry during the Spanish-American War
  - Photos (arranged by location)
    - Barry County (church, historic sites, Thornapple River) (Box 2)
    - Belle Isle (Box 2)
    - Bonneyville (mill) (Box 2)
    - Bradley (Indian mission) (Box 2)
    - Breedsville (hotel) (Box 2)
    - Cass County (mill, churches) (Box 2)
    - Cassopolis (homes, museum) (Box 2)
    - Centreville (county courthouse) (Box 2)
    - Climax (businesses; residences) (Box 2)
    - Coldwater (residence) (Box 2)
    - Constantine (mill; residences) (Box 2)
    - Cressey (log cabin residence of Indian chief) (Box 2)
    - Decatur (Catholic church) (Box 2)
    - Fort Custer (includes WW II prisoners of war) (Box 2)
    - Galesburg (tavern and home) (Box 2)
    - Grand Island (Box 2)
    - Grand Ledge (river ledges) (Box 2)
    - Gun Lake (Box 2)
    - Harbor Point (Harbor Springs lighthouse) 1898 (Box 2)
    - Hartfold (Indian mission) (Box 2)
    - Hastings (train wreck, mill, buildings, hardware store, 1917 military parade) (Box 2)
    - Iosco County (church) (Box 2)
    - Kalamazoo (Masonic Temple; early taverns) (Box 2)
    - Kalamazoo County (lake views; buildings) (Box 2)
    - Kane Creek (log cabin) (Box 2)
    - Kent County (log school house) (Box 2)
    - Leonidas (mill) (Box 2)
    - Lowell (historic site) (Box 2)
    - Mackinac Island (buildings and landmarks) 1898 (Box 2)
    - Marcellus (mill) (Box 2)
    - Middle Village (Box 2)
    - Middleville (Box 2)
    - Monroe (Custer monument) (Box 2)
    - Montmorency County (Black River) 1894 (Box 2)
    - Mottville (site of covered bridge) (Box 2)
    - Niles (historic sites) (Box 2)
    - Orangeville (mill; cove site; tavern) (Box 2)
    - Paw Paw (court house) (Box 2)
    - Richland (residence) (Box 2)
    - Rush Lake (historic sites) (Box 2)
    - St. Joseph County (fountain and fort) (Box 2)
    - Saugatuck (ferry scow; pavilion) (Box 2)
    - Sault Ste. Marie (sites and ships) 1898 (Box 2)
    - Schoolcraft (house and church) (Box 2)
    - Sturgis (hospital) (Box 2)
    - Three Oaks (Dewey cannon) (Box 2)
    - Union City (underground railway station) (Box 2)
    - Van Buren Park (memorial) (Box 2)
    - Vanderbilt (lumber camp) 1894 (Box 2)
    - White Pigeon (hotels; homes) (Box 2)
  - Photos (arranged by subject)
    - Hotels and taverns (include stage stops) (Box 2)
    - Indians (Box 2)
    - Indian trails (Thornapple Lake and river) (Box 2)
    - Lumbering (Box 2)
    - Mills (Box 2)
    - Shipyard (Box 2)
  - Photos (arranged by names of individuals)
    - Aiken, Martha D.Z. (Box 4)
    - Aliber, Jacob S. (Box 4)
    - Bennett, Luther (Box 4)
    - Bessemer, George (Box 4)
    - Bishop, Mr. and Mrs. Arthur (Box 4)
    - Bronson, Titus (Box 4)
    - Bryant, John M. (Box 4)
    - Carleton, Will (school where he taught) (Box 4)
    - Cisler, Joseph (Box 4)
    - Cook, Charles F. (Box 4)
    - Couture, Joe (Box 4)
    - Darling, James M. (Box 4)
    - Devine, William (Box 4)
    - Fellows, Abiel (Box 4)
      (portrait and photo of house)
    - Fish, Fidus E. (Box 4)
    - Fitzgerald, Leonard O. (Box 4)
    - Fitzgerald, Sarah A. (Box 4)
    - Hart, Thomas C. (Box 4)
    - Hickey, Rev. M. (Box 4)
    - Hinman, Eratus (Box 4)
    - Hodgman, Francis (Box 4)
    - Hoppin, Ruth (Box 4)
    - Ingram, Amos (Box 4)
    - Judson, William (Box 4)
    - Kittinger, G.L. (Box 4)
    - Langer, W.J. (Box 4)
    - Lewis, Robert (Box 4)
    - Longstreet, Andrew (Box 4)
    - Mason, Cornelius (Box 4)
    - Maynard, Myron (Box 4)
    - McNaughton, Peter (Box 4)
    - Magruder, Bruce (Maj. Gen.) (Box 4)
    - :Moseley, George (Box 4)
    - Nichols, Eli (Box 4)
    - Orr, E.A. (Box 4)
    - Parker, Frank (Maj. Gen.) (Box 4)
    - Pierce, Monte K. (Box 4)
    - Porter, George B. (Box 4)
    - Reed, Charles A. (Box 4)
    - Rice, Frank G. (Box 4)
    - Riley, Steven (Box 4)
    - Shafter, William Rufus (Box 4)
    - Shaver, Abram I. (Box 4)
    - Skinner, M.L. (Box 4)
    - Sleight, Alfred C. (Box 4)
    - Smith, William Alden (Box 4)
    - Striker, Elizabeth (Box 4)
    - Stroud, H.H. (Box 4)
    - Toll, Isaac (Box 4)
    - Weiner, George (judge) (Box 4)
    - Wells, Edwin Morris (Box 4)
    - Wickham, John (Box 4)